{"tossups": [{"question": "In one speech hosted by Marc Leder, this man called himself \u201cas poor as a church mouse\u201d and noted that \u201cI\u2019ll never convince them they should take personal responsibility and care for their lives,\u201d noting that his message \u201cdoesn\u2019t connect.\u201d In that fundraising speech, this man argued that, \u201cno matter what,\u201d47% of people will vote for President Obama. For the point, name this candidate whose ticket with Paul Ryan earned, coincidentally, 47% of the popular vote in the 2012 presidential election.", "answer": "Willard \u201cMitt\u201d<b> Romney</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man obtained a copy of every book published in his realm with the Ordonnance of Montpelier, and the Ordonnance of Villiers-Cotter\u02c6ets replaced Latin as the bureaucratic language with French. The Affair of the Placards hardened this man\u2019s attitude against Protestants. and this man attempted to form an alliance with Henry VIII at the Field of the Cloth of Gold. For the point, name this French monarch, who patronized Leonardo da Vinci and lost to his archrival Charles V at the Battle of Pavia.", "answer": "<b> Francis I</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The document NSC-68 supported this policy, as did a work analyzed by Clark Clifford and George Elsey, the Long Telegram. This policy was criticized by Barry Goldwater, who instead asked, \u201cWhy not victory?\u201d James Forrestal was called the \u201cgodfather\u201d of this policy for disseminating the X Article. Alternate strategies to this policy were isolationism, detente and rollback. This policy, created by George Kennan, inspired the Truman Doctrine and Marshall Plan, along with the creation of NATO. For the point, name this policy that sought to restrict the advance of Communism during the Cold War.", "answer": "<b> containment</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This nation arrested the Mamluk sphere of influence at the Battle of Diu, and it will supposedly lead a grand \u201c5th Empire.\u201d Zumbi led Palmares in opposition to this nation\u2019s imperialism. A general from this nation captured the island of Ormuz from Ismail I, in addition to the city of Goa. One of this nation\u2019s colonies contained quilombos and was east of the demarcation line of the Treaty of Tordesillas. For the point, name this empire that dominated 16th century Indian Ocean trade and colonized Brazil.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Portugal</b> (or<b> Portuguese</b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The bottom of this work was intended to depict plants with their roots visible in the soil. Statues of Jupiter and a headless Caesar flank this work, whose center shows a hand with a glowing orb. Its artist proposed adding Abraham Lincoln to the left side, but Nelson Rockefeller ordered it destroyed anyway. <em>Man, Controller of the Universe</em> is a recreation in Mexico of, for the point, what Diego Rivera mural that controversially depicted Vladimir Lenin?", "answer": "<b> Man at the Crossroads</b> (accept<b> Man, Controller of the Universe</b> before \u201cdestroyed\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Submarines supplied chocolate and Chelsea-brand cigarettes labeled with this phrase in order to boost morale amongst guerrilla fighters. This phrase was first used in a speech that spoke of the necessity of advancing from Corregidor to Australia and was fulfilled after the battle of Leyte Gulf. This promise was given after the failed defense of Bataan and subsequent fall of Luzon in 1941. For the point, give this three word promise spoken by Douglas Macarthur after leaving the Philippines.", "answer": "<b> \u201dI Shall Return\u201d</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This party discussed the rehabilitation of its country\u2019s military in the Himmerod memorandum. The Black Money exposed this party\u2019s secret bank accounts, which disgraced its former leader, Helmut Kohl. This party\u2019s leaders Ludwig Erhard and Konrad Adenauer sparked an \u201ceconomic miracle\u201d in its country post-World War II, and it has participated in various \u201cGrand Coalitions\u201d with the Social Democratic Party. For the point, name this center-right political party in Germany, currently led by Angela Merkel.", "answer": "<b> C</b>hristian<b> D</b>emocratic<b> U</b>nion (accept the<b> Christian Democrat</b>ic party)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Pierre Falcone and Charles Pasqua coordinated arm sales from France to this country in the 1990s. A guerilla war broke out in this country after Jonas Savimbi rejected the results of a 1992 election. The Bicesse Accord ended a civil war in this country between UNITA and the MPLA. This country which gained independence by the Alvor Agreement is currently led by Jose Eduardo dos Santos. For the point, name this former Portuguese colony north of Namibia whose capital is Luanda.", "answer": "<b> Angola</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This work\u2019s introduction notes that a warring country was \u201cmoved by insane delusion and reckless self-regard,\u201d but that their opponents \u201chave run the risk of completing the ruin.\u201d It calculates a sum of ten billion dollars for claimed losses that would have been \u201ca wise and just act to have asked [for].\u201d This work argues against a \u201cCarthaginian peace\u201d that would exist if Georges Clemenceau\u2019s proposed reparations were authorized. For the point, name this 1919 book written by John Maynard Keynes [CANES] after he left the Paris Peace Conference in frustration at the negotiations of the Treaty of Versailles.", "answer": "The<b> Economic Consequences of the Peace</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "Storm Delarverie may have sparked this event after crying out \u201cWhy don\u2019t you guys do something?\u201dThree years prior to this event, a similar event occurred at the Compton Cafeteria in San Francisco. The Genovese mob owned the Christopher Street establishment where this event began. Participants in this event were said to have \u201clost that wounded look.\u201d Seymour Pine led the police response to this event in Greenwich Village. The Gay Liberation Front was formed after, for the point, what June 1969 riot in New York City?", "answer": "<b> Stonewall</b> (Inn) riots", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "According to a false legend, the first person in this position was responsible for German not becoming an official language of the United States; that man was Frederick Muhlenberg. Dan Webster received nine protest votes for this position in 2015, while Colin Powell received one vote, as the Constitution allows this Congressional position to be held by someone who is not a member of Congress. In 2016, a former holder of this position, Dennis Hastert, was accused of sexual misconduct. For the point, name this political position, currently held by Paul Ryan, which sets Agenda in the lower house of Congress.", "answer": "<b> Speaker of the House</b> of Representatives", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One member of this tribe, John Ross, controversially broke with other members in negotiating an agreement with the U.S. government. This tribe gained almost two million acres of land from the Creek in the Treaty of Fort Jackson after assisting Andrew Jackson in fighting at Horseshoe Bend. In that battle, one member of this tribe saw \u201ctalking leaves,\u201d inspiring him to develop a syllabary for this tribe. The Treaty of New Echota forced this tribe onto the Trail of Tears. Sequoyah was a member of, for the point, what southeastern Native American tribe, the largest to be federally recognized?", "answer": "<b> Cherokee</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This poet wrote \u201cBe patient and strong; someday, this pain will be useful to you\u201d in a collection of love poetry that focuses on a married woman named Corinna. That collection,<em> Amores</em>, along with the later<em> Ars Amatoria</em>, may have led Augustus to exile this poet to Tomis. Book one of a fifteen-book work by this author includes the story of Daphne, who is saved from the chasing Apollo when she is turned into a laurel tree. For the point, name this Roman poet of<em> Metamorphoses</em>.", "answer": "<b> Ovid</b> (or Publius<b> Ovid</b>ius Naso)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "A lack of proper uniforms among this man\u2019s troops caused Phineas Riall to treat them as militia in the Battle of Chippewa. This man captured a fort defended by six \u201cHeroic Cadets\u201d and Nicolas Bravo, and he commanded alongside Jacob Brown at the Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane. This general produced a strategy to control waterways in order to strangle the South. For the point, name this long-serving Union general, a victor of Chapultepec who designed the Anaconda Plan.", "answer": "Winfield<b> Scott</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "After this game, the winning coach noted that \u201cDetroit has had\u201d Hank Stram\u2019s defense \u201cfor years.\u201dIn this game, Willie Wood returned a Len Dawson interception 50 yards and Max McGree caught two touchdowns from Bart Starr. In January 2016, a compilation broadcast of all of this game\u2019s plays was broadcast on NFL Network on its 49th anniversary. For the point, name this game in which Green Bay defeated Kansas City in the first AFL-NFL World Championship Game.", "answer": "<b> Super Bowl 1</b> (accept<b> first AFL-NFL World Championship Game</b> before \u201cAFL\u201d is said)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A precursor to this organization known as the Interfactory Strike Committee issued the 21 Demands. This organization was founded after the firing of crane worker Anna Walentynowicz [vah-lent-ee-noh-vich]. Social unrest in one country led this organization to participate in the Round Table Talks after it was banned by General Jaruzelski [yar-oo-zel-skee]. This organization was co-founded and led by an electrical worker at the Lenin Shipyard in Gdansk. For the point, name this Polish anti-Communist party that began as a trade union led by Lech Walesa.", "answer": "<b> Solidarity</b> (or<b> Solidarno\u00b4s\u00b4c</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A three-time holder of this position had his official portrait controversially painted by Don Bachardy. One holder of the position signed the Therapeutic Abortion Act, having gained this position by defeating George Christopher a year after delivering the \u201cA Time For Choosing\u201d speech at a national convention. In 2003, Gray Davis was recalled from this position in favor of, for the second time in its history, a popular actor. For the point, name this position held by Jerry Brown, Ronald Reagan, and Arnold Schwarzenegger.", "answer": "<b> Governor of California</b> (prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man negotiated the Treaty of Mon\u00b8con with Gaspar de Guzm\u00b4an, a Spanish diplomat. Sweden was persuaded to ally with this man\u2019s nation through the Treaty of Barwalde. Henry de Cinq Mars opposed this man, as did a series of advisors who thought they had ousted this man on the Day of the Dupes. This enemy of the Huguenots personally conquered one of their last strongholds at La Rochelle. For the point, name this man, known as the Red Eminence, a French cardinal who advised Louis XIII.", "answer": "Cardinal de<b> Richelieu</b> (or Armand-Jean du<b> Plessis</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This figure and Barack Obama are studied in Erik Schneiderman\u2019s<em> The Size of Others\u2019 Burdens</em>. Leo Tolstoy criticized this woman\u2019s sleeves and described her as an \u201cabsentee landlord,\u201d as her farm was one hundred miles away from her work on Halsted Street. This first American woman to win a Nobel Peace Prize worked closely with Ellen Gates Starr. For the point, name this early 20th century advocate for women and the poor who co-founded a settlement house in Chicago, Hull House.", "answer": "Jane<b> Addams</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One plan for the construction of these objects involved the use of pykrete, a mixture of wood pulp and ice, and was named Project Habakkuk. The Tondern Raid was one of the first attacks using these objects, and the Ark Royal was a merchant ship converted to become the first of these objects. These objects come in CATOBAR and ski-jump varities, and the Fairey Swordfish that launched from one of these objects torpedoed the Italian navy at Taranto. For the point, name this type of ship whose flat deck allows for takeoffs and landings.", "answer": "aircraft<b> carriers</b> (prompt on generic words like \u201cship\u201d before ship is said; do not accept or prompt other types of ships)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man established a torture center at the Nile Mansions and created paramilitary police forces called the Public Safety Unit and State Research Bureau. This man, who was overthrown after a failed attempt to annex Kagera from Tanzania, came to power after leading an attack on King Mutesa II\u2019s palace and, five years later, seizing total power while Milton Obote [oh-boh-tay] was abroad. For the point, name this self-proclaimed \u201cLord of All the Beasts of the Earth\u201d who expelled all Asians from Uganda.", "answer": "<b> Idi Amin</b> Dada", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this event, Pete Smerick and Mark Young wrote a memo warning against increasing federal pressure. This event took place at the Mount Carmel Center, home to a Seventh-Day Adventist sect that was suspected of weapons violations; as a result, Janet Reno approved FBI intervention, leading to the deaths of 76 people when the compound burned down during a tear gas attack by federal agents. For the point, name this 1993 siege of David Koresh\u2019s community of Branch Davidians, commonly called by the Texas city near the compound.", "answer": "<b> Waco</b> siege (accept descriptions of the<b> Branch Davidian</b> siege or the siege on David <b>Koresh</b>\u2019s compound before \u201cDavid\u201d is said)", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}